I was born and raised in Dakar, Senegal,
وُلدت في داكار في السنغال ونشأت فيها،
and through a combination of accidents and cosmic justice,
وعن طريق الدمج بين الصُدف والعدالة الكونية،
became a chef in the US.
صرت طاهيًا في أمريكا.
When I first arrived in New York,
عندما وصلت إلى نيويورك لأول مرة،
I began working in these restaurants -- different types of restaurants --
بدأت بالعمل في المطاعم... أنواع مختلفة من المطاعم...
from French bistro to Italian,
من المطاعم الفرنسية الصغيرة إلى الإيطالية،
global ethnic to modern American.
إلى عرقية عالمية إلى الأمريكية العصرية.
At the time,
حينذاك،
New York was already well-established as a food capital of the world.
كانت نيويورك معروفة بعاصمة الأكل للعالم.
However ...
إلا أن...
with the exception of a few West African and Ethiopian mom-and-pop eateries,
باستثناء القليل من المأكولات الأفريقية الغربية والأثيوبية،
there was no such thing as African cuisine in the entire city.
فإنه لا يوجد ما يسمى بالمطبخ الأفريقي في المدينة كلها.
Early in my life,
في فترة مبكرة في حياتي،
I was influenced by Senegal's first president,
كنت مُتأثرًا بأول رئيس للسنغال،
Léopold Sédar Senghor,
ليوبولد سيدار سنغور،
nicknamed, "the poet president,"
الملقب "بالرئيس الشاعر،"
who talked about a new humanism,
الذي تحدث عن الإنسانية الجديدة،
a universal civilization,
والحضارة العالمية،
in which all cultures would come together around a communal table as equals,
حيث تجتمع كل الحضارات بطريقة متساوية حول طاولة كوميونية،
each bringing its own beautiful contribution to share.
كل واحد منهم يساهم بمساهمة جميلة ليشاركها.
He called it "the rendezvous of giving and receiving."
أطلق عليها "موعد الأخذ والعطاء."
That concept resonated with me,
ذلك المفهوم بقي في ذاكرتي،
and it has guided my career path.
وقاد مساري الوظيفي.
After years of working in restaurants,
وبعد سنوات من العمل في المطاعم،
I yearned for my work to have a deeper impact
تطلّعت في عملي أن أصل إلى تأثير أعمق
that would go beyond the last meal I had served.
يتجاوز آخر وجبة قدمتها.
I wanted to give back, both to New York --
أردت ردّ الجميل لكل من نيويورك...
the city that allowed me the opportunity to follow my calling --
المدينة التي سمحت لي بفرصة متابعة شغفي...
but also to my origins and ancestors in Senegal.
ولكن أيضًا لأصولي وأجدادي في السنغال.
I wanted to contribute to that universal civilization
أردت المساهمة في تلك الحضارة العالمية
Senghor had described.
التي وصفها سنغور.
But I didn't know how to make a measurable impact
ولكن لم أعلم كيف أترك أثرًا ملموسًا
as a cook and writer.
كطبّاخ وكاتب.
While I was writing my first cookbook,
عند كتابتي لأول كتاب طبخ،
I often traveled to different regions of Senegal for research.
سافرت كثيرًا لمناطق مختلفة في السنغال لإجراء بحث.
During one of those trips,
وخلال واحدة من هذه الرحلات،
in the remote, southeast region of Kédougou
في المناطق النائية جنوب شرق منطقة كيدوغو
I rediscovered an ancient grain called fonio
اكتشفت حبوب قديمة تسمى بالفونيو
that had all but disappeared from the urban Senegalese diet.
والتي تحتوي على كل شيء ولكن اختفت من حمية السنغاليين المتمدنين.
It turns out that fonio had been cultivated
واتضح بأن الفونيو كانت تُزرع
for more than five thousand years
منذ أكثر من خمسة آلاف سنة
and is probably the oldest cultivated cereal in Africa.
وقد تكون أقدم الحبوب زراعةً في أفريقيا.
Once a popular grain on much of the continent,
أحد أشهر الحبوب على معظم أنحاء القارة،
fonio was grown all the way to ancient Egypt,
زُرع الفونيو في كل هذه المسافة حتى مصر القديمة،
where archaeologists found grains inside pyramids' burial grounds.
حيث وجد علماء الآثار الحبوب داخل مقابر الأهرامات.
Today it is mostly cultivated in the western part of the Sahel region,
واليوم هي أكثر ما يزرع في الجزء الغربي لمنطقة الساحل،
from Senegal to Mali,
من السنغال إلى مالي،
Burkina Faso,
بوركينا فاسو،
Togo, Nigeria.
توجو ونيجيريا.
The Sahel region is that semiarid area south of the Sahara desert
منطقة الساحل هي منطقة شبه قاحلة جنوب الصحراء الكبرى
that extends from the Atlantic in the west to the Red Sea in the east.
تمتد من المحيط الأطلسي في الغرب إلى البحر الأحمر في الشرق
I became more interested in this grain
أصبحتُ مهتمًا أكثر بهذه الحبوب
that was deemed worth taking to the afterlife by early Egyptians.
التي اعتبرها المصرييون القدماء حبوب تستحق أخذها إلى ما بعد الممات.
As I continued my research,
بينما كنت أواصل بحثي،
I found out that fonio was actually --
وجدت بأن الفونيو في الواقع...
wherever it was cultivated --
أينما كان يزرع...
there was always some myth, or some superstition connected to it.
دائمًا ما كانت تحيط به الأساطير أو معتقد خرافي مرتبط به.
The Dogon,
قبيلة الدوجون،
another great culture in Mali,
ثقافة عظيمة أخرى في مالي،
called it "po,"
سمته "بو،"
or, "the seed of the universe."
أو "بذور العالم."
In that ancient culture's mythology,
وفي أسطورة تلك الثقافة القديمة،
the entire universe sprouted from a seed of fonio.
نبت العالم بأكمله من بذور الفونيو.
Aside from its purported mystical properties,
وبغض النظر عن خصائصها الغامضة المزعومة،
fonio is a miracle grain in many aspects.
الفونيو حبوب خارقة في عدة جوانب.
It is nutritious,
فهي مغذّية،
particularly rich in methionine and cysteine,
وغنية خاصة بالميثونين وسيستياين،
two amino acids that are deficient in most other major grains:
حمضان أمينيان تفتقر إليها الكثير من الحبوب الرئيسة:
barley, rice or wheat to name a few.
كالشعير والأرز والقمح على سبيل المثال لا الحصر.
In addition,
بالإضافة إلى،
fonio cultivation is great for the environment.
زراعة الفونيو جيدة للبيئة.
It tolerates poor soil
تتحمل ضعف خصوبة التربة
and needs very little water,
وتحتاج إلى القليل من الماء،
surviving where nothing else will grow.
وتنمو حيث لا يمكن لغيرها النمو.
As a chef,
وبصفتي طاهٍ،
what first struck me was its delicate taste and its versatility.
أول ما أدهشني هو طعمها الشهي وتعدد استعمالاتها.
Similar to couscous,
شبيه بالكسكس،
fonio has a delicious, nutty and earthy flavor.
للفونيو نكهة جوزيّة وترابية لذيذة.
It can be turned into salad,
يمكن تحويله إلى سلطة،
served as noodles,
أو يقدم كنودل،
used in baking
يُستخدم في الخَبْز
or simply as a substitute for any other grains in your favorite recipes.
أو ببساطة بديل لأي حبوب في وصفاتك المفضلة.
I am happy to share some of my fonio sushi and sweet potato sushi
يسعدني أن أشارككم بعضًا من أطباق سوشي الفونيو وسوشي البطاطا الحلوة
with some of you right now.
مع البعض منكم الآن.
(Audience) Oh!
(تصفيق)
And okra.
والبامية.
In Kédougou
في كيدوغو
it is also nicknamed "ñamu buur,"
يلقب أيضًا "بنامي بور،"
which means "food for royalty,"
وذلك يعني "طعام الملوك،"
and it's served for guests of honor.
ويقدّم لضيوف الشرف.
Located at the border with Guinea and Mali,
يقع في الحدود بين غينيا ومالي،
Kédougou first strikes visitors with its stunning vistas
كيدوغو تدهش الزائرين بآفاق
and views of the Fouta Djallon Mountains.
ومناظر جبال فوتا جالون الساحرة.
Sadly, it is also one of the poorest regions of Senegal.
وللأسف، هي أحد أفقر مناطق السنغال أيضًا.
Because of desertification and lack of job prospects,
وبسبب التصحّر وقلة فرص العمل،
much of Kédougou's young population has left.
هاجر معظم سكان كيدوجو الشباب.
They chose the deadly path of migration
اختاروا الطريق المميت للهجرة
in search of "better" opportunities.
للبحث عن فرص " أفضل."
Often,
والكثير منهم،
they risk their lives trying to reach Europe.
يخاطر بحياته ليصل إلى أوروبا.
Some leave by crossing the Sahara desert.
البعض يغادر عبر الصحراء الكبرى.
Others end up on inadequate wooden canoes
وآخرون ينتهي بهم المطاف على قوارب خشبية رديئة
in desperate attempts to reach Spain.
في محاولات يائسة للوصول إلى أسبانيا.
According to a recent "Guardian" article,
وفقًا لمقالة نُشرت مؤخرًا في "الجارديان"
by 2020 more that 60 million people from sub-Saharan Africa
بحلول عام 2020 أكثر من 60 مليون شخص من أفريقيا جنوب الصحراء
are expected to migrate
يتوقع هجرتهم
due to desertification.
بسبب التصحّر.
This is the biggest global wave of migration since the Second World War,
وهذه أضخم موجة هجرة منذ الحرب العالمية الثانية،
and it's only set to grow.
ويحتمل زيادتها فقط.
So far this year,
هذا العام حتى الآن،
more that 2,100 migrants have lost their lives
فقد أكثر من 2100 مهاجر حياته
on their way to Europe.
في طريقه إلى أوروبا.
This is the reality of Kédougou
هذا واقع كيدوغو
and of much of the Sahel today.
ومعظم مناطق الساحل اليوم.
Scary future,
مستقبل مُخيف،
scarce food
وغذاء شحيح
and no opportunities to change their situation.
ولا فرص لتغيير أوضاعهم.
If life in your village weren't so precarious,
لو لم تكن الحياة في قريتك خطرة جدًا،
if there was a way to having enough food to get by,
ولو كانت هنالك طريقة للحصول على الطعام الكافي لسد الحاجة،
or having a paying job --
أو الحصول على عمل بأجر...
if you and your sisters
لو كنت أنت وإخوتك
didn't have to spend 30 percent of their waking hours
لم تضطروا لقضاء 30% من ساعات اليقظة
fetching water,
لإحضار الماء،
if conditions were just a little more hospitable ...
لو كانت الظروف مُلائمة قليلًا...
could the solution be right here in our soil?
هل سيكون الحل هنا في تربتنا؟
Could bringing fonio to the rest of the world
هل سيكون تقديم الفونيو لبقية العالم
be the answer?
هو الحل؟
Ancient grains are getting more popular,
الحبوب القديمة تزداد شهرة،
and sales of gluten-free items are growing in the US --
ومبيعات المنتجات الخالية من الجلوتين انتعشت في الولايات المتحدة...
16.4 percent since 2013,
بنسبة 16.4% منذ عام 2013
making it a 23.3-billion-dollar industry.
مما جعلها صناعة تساوي 23.3 مليار دولار.
How could fonio partake in this market share?
كيف يمكن للفونيو أن تشارك في نصيبها من السوق؟
There are many challenges in turning fonio into food.
توجد العديد من التحديات لتحويل الفونيو إلى طعام.
Traditional processing is laborious and time-consuming,
العملية التقليدية مُجهِدة وتستهلك الكثير من الوقت،
especially when compared to other grains.
خاصة عند مقارنتها بالحبوب الأخرى.
Well, thankfully, technology has evolved.
حسنًا، لحسن الحظ أن التقنية تطورت.
And there are now machines
وهنالك الآن آلات
that can process fonio in a more efficient way.
يمكنها معالجة الحبوب بكفاءة أكبر.
And as a matter of fact,
وفي الحقيقة،
a few years ago,
قبل عدة سنوات،
Sanoussi Diakité,
سنوسي جاكيتي،
a Senegalese engineer,
مهندس سنغالي،
won a Rolex prize
فاز بجائزة روليكس
for his invention of the first mechanized fonio processor.
لاختراعه أول معالج آلي للفونيو.
Today, such machines are making life much easier for producers
اليوم، مثل هذه الآلات تجعل الحياة أكثر سهولة للمنتجين
around the whole Sahel region.
حول منطقة الساحل بأكملها.
Another challenge is the colonial mentality
والتحدي الآخر هو العقلية الاستعمارية
that what comes from the west is best.
بأن ما يأتي من الغرب هو الأفضل.
This tendency to look down on our own products
الميل إلى تحقير منتجاتنا
and to see crops like fonio as simply "country peoples' food,"
ورؤية المحاصيل مثل الفونيو ببساطة على أنه "طعام أهل المدينة"
therefore substandard,
ولذلك هي متدنية المستوى،
explains why even though we don't produce wheat in Senegal traditionally,
يُفسِر لماذا بالرغم من أننا لا ننتج القمح في السنغال عادة،
it is far easier to find baguettes or croissants in the streets of Dakar
إلا أنه من السهل إيجاد الخبز الفرنسي أو الكروسون في شوارع داكار
than it is to find any fonio products.
عن إيجاد أي منتج من منتجات فونيو.
This same mindset popularized the overprocessed, leftover rice debris
نفس العقلية هذه روّجت لبقايا فتات الأرز المُعالج
known as "broken rice,"
المعروف بالأرز المكسّر،
which was imported to Senegal from Indochina
الذي استورِد إلى السنغال من الهند الصينية
and introduced by the colonial French.
وأدخله الاستعمار الفرنسي.
Soon, broken rice became a key ingredient in our national dish,
ما إن دخل الأرز المكسّر أصبح عنصر أساسي في طبقنا الوطني،
thiéboudienne,
الثيبودين،
replacing our own traditional, more nutritious African rice,
باستبدالنا أرزنا الأفريقي التقليدي والمغذّي أكثر،
Oryza glaberrima.
أوريزا جلابريما.
Ironically, the same African rice despised at home
ومن السخرية بأن نفس الأرز الأفريقي المُحتقر في المنزل
was hailed abroad.
رُحّب به في الخارج.
Indeed, during the Atlantic slave trade,
بالفعل، وفي فترة تجارة الرقيق عبر المحيط الأطلسي،
this rice became a major crop in the Americas ...
أصبح الأرز محصول رئيس في أمريكا...
particularly in the Carolinas
بالتحديد في كارولاينا
where it was nicknamed, "Carolina gold."
حيث لُقّب "بذهب كارولاينا."
But let's return to fonio.
ولكن لنعود إلى الفونيو.
How can we turn its current status of "country-people food"
كيف نحوّل وضعه الحالي من "طعام أهل المدينة"
into a world-class crop?
إلى محصول ذو مستوى عالمي؟
Last year,
العام الماضي،
a business partner and I secured a commitment from Whole Foods Market,
أنا وشريك تجاري ضمنا الالتزامات من هول فودز ماركت،
the US's largest natural food store chain,
أكبر سلسلة محلات الأطعمة الطبيعية في الولايات المتحدة،
to carry fonio.
ليبيع الفونيو.
And we got a large American ingredient importer
وحصلنا على مُستورِد مواد غذائية أمريكي كبير
interested enough to send a team of executives
لديه الاهتمام الكافي لإرسال فريق من المدراء التنفيذيون
to West Africa with us
إلى غرب أفريقيا معنا
to explore the supply chain's viability.
لاستكشاف جدوى سلسلة الإمداد.
We found ourselves observing manual operations
وجدنا أنفسنا ننظر إلى العمليات اليدوية
in remote locations
في مواقع بعيدة
with few controls over quality.
بتحكّم محدود في الجودة.
So we started focusing on processing issues.
لذا بدأنا نركز على مشاكل المعالجة
We drew up a vision
رسمنا رؤية
with a beneficial and commercially sustainable supply chain for fonio,
سلسلة إمداد للفونيو تعود بالنفع ومستدامة تجاريًا،
and we connected ourselves with organizations
وربطنا أنفسنا بالمنظمات
that can help us achieve it.
التي يمكنها مساعدتنا في تحقيق ذلك
Walking backwards from the market, here is what it looks like.
المشي بالعكس من السوق هكذا يبدو.
Imagine that fonio is consumed all across the globe
تخيلوا بأن الفونيو يُستهلك حول العالم
as other popular ancient grains.
مثل الحبوب القديمة المشهورة الأخرى.
Fonio touted on the levels of cereals,
يُباع الفونيو على مراحل الحبوب،
breads,
الخبز،
nutrition bars,
ألواح المكملات الغذائية،
cookies, pastas,
الكوكيز والباستا،
snacks -- why not?
الوجبات الخفيفة ، لم لا؟
It's easier to say than quinoa.
هي أسهل نطقًا من الكينوا.
(Applause)
(ضحك)
To get there,
لبلوغ تلك الغاية،
fonio needs to be readily available
يحتاج الفونيو ليكون متاح بسهولة
at a consistent quality for commercial users,
بجودة ملائمة للمستخدمين التجاريين،
such as food manufacturers and restaurant chains.
مثل مصنعي الأغذية وسلاسل المطاعم.
That's the part we're missing.
هذا الجزء الذي ينقصنا.
To make fonio available at a consistent quality
لنجعل الفونيو متاح بجودة ملائمة
for commercial use,
للاستخدام التجاري،
you need a commercial-scale fonio mill
تحتاج إلى مصنع فونيو ذا نطاق تجاري
that adheres to international quality standards.
يلتزم بمعايير الجودة العالمية.
Currently, there is no such mill in the whole world,
حاليًا، لايوجد مصنع بهذه المواصفات في العالم كله،
so in our vision,
لذا في رؤيتنا،
there is an African-owned and operated fonio mill
يتواجد مصنع فونيو تمتلكه أفريقيا وتشغله
that processes efficiently
ويعالج بكفاءة
and in compliance with the requirements of multinational food companies.
ويتماشى مع متطلبات شركات الأغذية متعددة الجنسيات.
It is very difficult for the fonio producers today
يصعب على منتجي الفونيو اليوم
to sell and use fonio
بيع الفونيو واستخدامه
unless they devote a huge amount of time and energy
إلا في حال تكريس قدر كبير من الطاقة والوقت
in threshing, winnowing and husking it.
في دَرْس المحصول وتذريته وتقشيره.
In our vision,
في رؤيتنا،
the mill will take on those tasks,
سيتولى المصنع هذه المهام،
allowing the producers to focus on farming rather than processing.
وبذلك يسمح للمنتجين التركيز على الزراعة بدلًا من المعالجة.
There is untapped agricultural capacity in the Sahel,
يوجد إمكانات زراعية غير مستغلة في الساحل،
and all it takes is changing market conditions
وكل ما يتطلبه الأمر هو تغيير حالة السوق
to activate that capacity.
لتفعيل هذه الإمكانات.
By relieving fonio producers of manual operations,
بإعفاء منتجي الفونيو من العمليات اليدوية،
the mill will free up their time
ستوفر الطاحونة لهم الوقت
and remove the production bottleneck that limits their output.
ويزيل عنق الزجاجة للانتاج التي تحدّ نتاجهم
And there are other benefits as well
وهنالك عدة فوائد أيضًا
in using Sahel land for agriculture.
في استخدام أرض الساحل للزراعة.
More benefits,
فوائد أكثر،
higher employment,
نسبة توظيف أعلى،
climate change mitigation by reversing desertification
الحدّ من آثار تغيّر الطقس عن طريق القضاء على التصحّر
and greater food security.
وأمان غذائي أكبر.
Nice vision, right?
رؤية جميلة، أليس كذلك؟
Well, we are working towards getting it done.
نحن نعمل لتحقيقها.
Last month we introduced fonio to shoppers in New York City
الشهر الماضي قدّمنا الفونيو لمتسوقي مدينة نيويورك
and online,
على الانترنت،
in a package that makes it attractive and desirable and accessible.
في حزمة تجعلها مغرية وجذابة ومُتاحة.
We are talking with operators and investors in West Africa
نحن نتحدث مع المشغلين والمستثمرين في غرب أفريقيا
about building a fonio mill.
عن إنشاء مصنع فونيو.
And most importantly,
والأهم من هذا،
we have teamed with an NGO called SOS SAHEL
شكّلنا فريق مع منظمة غير حكومية يطلق عليها إس أو أس ساحل
to recruit, train and equip smallholders in the Sahel
لتوظيف وتدريب وتأهيل صغار الملاك في الساحل
to increase their fonio production.
لزيادة إنتاجهم في الفونيو.
Hunger levels are higher in sub-Saharan Africa
مستويات الجوع أعلى في أفريقيا جنوب الصحراء الكبرى
than any other place in the world.
من أي مكان آخر في العالم.
The Sahel population is set to grow
سكان الساحل في نمو وتزايد
from 135 million to 340 million people.
من 135 مليون نسمة إلى 340 مليون نسمة.
However, in that drought- and famine-prone region,
إلا أن في منطقة الجفاف والمعرضة للمجاعة،
fonio grows freely.
ينمو الفونيو بحرية.
This tiny grain may provide big answers,
هذا المحصول الصغير يقدّم الإجابات الكبيرة،
reasserting its Dogon name,
ليؤكد اسمه الذي أطلقته قبيلة دوغون،
"po," the seed of the universe,
"بو" بذرة العالم،
and taking us one step closer
ويأخذنا خطوة واحدة إلى الأمام
to the universal civilization.
للحضارة العالمية.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.